Hello and welcome back to another
episode with ItsDrDan . And today
we're gonna learn all about electron
configuration and to how to use the
tools that you have around you during an
exam so that way you are able to ace it.
Um, the one thing you're given
on every test in any class
is always a peer act table.
Trying to memorize all these
different methods on how to
solve electron configuration
can be exhausting and difficult.
So let's learn how to use the
resources that are available to you.
Now let's get into it and try to
understand what is electron configuration.
Well, one thing that you learned about
back right before electron configuration
was this idea of the bore model.
The problem with it, it's not enough.
It does not talk about how
electrons, how they repel each other.
It doesn't describe exactly
how these methods work.
So what, why we need
electron configuration.
It's how we can exactly
organize ourselves.
Almost like the same way how you
might organize your kitchen, for
example, cups go in a certain
place, plates go somewhere, bowls go
somewhere, food goes somewhere else.
They all have their own set place.
Electron configuration is the same way.
So if I have this bore model up here
for chlorine, well we can do the
exact same thing and put things into
specific orbitals where they belong
rather than These orbits orbitals are
three dimensional picture for us to
tell us exactly where they're going.
Now we can show this in a
complete way or as well with
noble gas configuration as well.
So let's go into trying to understand
exactly what this entails and
what type of orbitals we will see.
There's different types of
orbitals that you will see.
They revolve around the following
letters of s, p, d, and f, which are
based on the shapes of the orbitals.
Of how they are located
around the nucleus of an atom.
Now each of these orbitals contain
a different number of electrons.
The first one, s, is one
of our lowest levels.
This one always has two
electrons in its orbital.
It only has one orbital to have those
two electrons With P, we have three
orbitals fitting six electrons in them.
And one thing that you can see
with that is, well, we have a trend
where we can only fit a total of
two electrons in every orbital.
Now, with D what we're gonna be seeing
there is now we're at five orbitals.
With those five orbitals, you can
fit a total of 10 electrons in them.
So what we always do is we fill
in orbitals from left to right,
we make sure everybody has their
own room first, and then we fill
in all the remaining electrons.
Our last one is F orbitals.
So with F we have seven orbitals
that are available to us and
they can each fit two electrons.
Now with all these different shapes,
what I'm going to be showing you next
is examples of each individual orbital.
But let's show how these are
situated on our Peer Act table,
so that way we're able to use it.
And that way you can use it
along with these examples and
try to solve them for yourself.
Our peer Act table looks a lot like
this, and you might have a very similar
one that maybe your teacher potentially
handed out to you for your course.
Um, it doesn't matter
exactly which one you have.
All of 'em have different
amounts of information on it.
Usually when you're in a class, alls
you're given is the elemental symbol,
the mass number, and the atomic number.
But we can still use this just to how,
show us how exactly we can organize it.
So let's first try to switch it up so that
way you can see it in a different light.
With the periodic table, the first
thing is you can kind of see there
are very general features around it.
Certain shapes, like for example, if you
see around this top column, there's an
area, there's this top column over here.
There seems to be this area
over here that's different
and also the area down here.
So let's switch it up.
Okay.
Change the picture up.
So what this is, is we
overlaid our periodic table
with all the general shapes.
That you are gonna be seeing
on your periodic table.
Our first two columns over here on the
left, this is referred to as our S block.
Notice how there are two columns here.
So the shapes tell you how many electrons.
If you remember ss, add two electrons and
we can see we have one, two columns there.
With P, right?
That had a total of six electrons.
We can see 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
The shape is in the table.
So trying to remember.
So trying to remember like the diagonal
method or all these other methods really
can't help you if you don't remember them.
So remember your shape.
So other things with D block that
could fit 10 electrons, right?
So we can see that here.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10.
And then the last one was the F block.
Well, F block down here is 1, 2, 3, 4,
5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, and 14.
Right?
We have all those individual pieces now.
That's not the only thing, though.
It's not only shape, it's
also based on energy level.
How can we tell energy?
Well, there's another
helpful thing, right?
We just counted a bunch of columns.
What about the rows?
So over here on the left hand side of
our periodic table, I put all these
individual numbers here as well.
These are referred to as n levels,
also known as your quantum level.
The way to view it is like walking
up, walking up, uh, flights of stairs
in like maybe a really tall building.
So you're start your first floor, you
walk up to your second, your third,
your fourth, your fifth, and the farther
you have to walk up, the higher it more
energy you have to use to get there.
It's very similar.
The farther you are from the
nucleus, the more energy, so we're
going to be using that as well.
Now, how can we actually be able
to show all these individual
levels of electronic configuration?
The way we're gonna read this
is like you're reading a book.
You start from the top and you
read from left to right, okay?
And then you go down a line, you read from
left to right, and we're gonna continue
across counting all of our orbitals.
So we start at ss, go all the
way over to P and so forth.
So let's look at a bunch of examples
here and here I have all the
orbitals listed in the exact order.
So if it's something you wanna write
down for yourself, you can, right?
It goes one S, two S, three S, and so on.
You can read all those there.
You can pause it.
Take note of that.
Let's go through some examples.
Let's start with our S orbital example.
Okay?
So for our first example, we're gonna
look at lithium, which is an ss, just
looking at the SS orbital configuration.
So earlier I mentioned that we're gonna
be reading our periodic table like a book.
So the first thing you want to do
is figure out exactly where do you
wanna stop reading of your book?
How many sentences do you wanna read?
Do you just wanna read one chapter or
you wanna read it from cover to cover?
Well, if it's like a science book, you
just wanna read the information you need.
So here we're going to go right
to Lithium, which is right here.
And what that tells you is
that we need a total of, or we
have a number of three on it.
Which we have a total of three
electrons, three protons.
So let's go through this.
How exactly do we start?
Well, we start from the top.
Well, like I said, we read across
our top row and that is gonna be
on number row number one, right?
So we can see that number one
there, um, that we saw earlier.
Now being that this is the s orbital
hydrogen and helium both have s orbitals.
So we will do 1s^2.
Now, being that that's our first
row, we're then gonna go down
to the second line of our book
ending at Lithium over here.
So that's gonna be our two sss.
Now, where do you stop?
Well, we're stopping at
the first column, right?
Right where lithium is.
So this is gonna be 1s^2, 2s^1.
Now that is just all you gotta do for
your complete configuration of lithium.
It gets pretty simple at first.
It gets more complicated
the farther we get down.
Now, one thing we can always do
for ourselves if we can abbreviate
these different structures.
So a Noble gas configuration is referring
to the last column of our periodic table.
I'm gonna turn that red
just so we can show it.
The noble gases is everything
that's on this column here, right?
So everything that's down here, Now
one thing you'll notice is that,
well, what noble gas is above it?
Above lithium, that is,
and that is helium, right?
If you look up one row up, you
can see helium is right here.
So what we can actually do is we can
abbreviate our configuration, which
stands for that one S two with helium,
and then just put helium to SS one.
Now.
For now, it doesn't seem like it
makes a lot of sense, but as we
go further down, abbreviating is
gonna make a lot of sense later.
Let's go onto a P orbital example.
Okay, with our next example.
For P.
For P orbital example,
let's look at silicon.
So with silicon, what we're gonna
be looking for is let's find
that on our periodic table, and
we can see that it's right here.
Now with this one, this
one has 14 electrons.
Now with this example, we're
gonna make sure I specify exactly
why we are saying that out loud.
There's a way for us to double
check ourselves, so let's move
some things over a little bit.
So we are gonna find the complete
configuration of silicon.
So once again, we're gonna start
the same way we start at the top.
And notice how I moved helium over here
to help show that s orbital configuration.
So that is our first level.
That is gonna be one SS two.
We're gonna go to our second line
of our book, see Lithium from last
one, and then beryllium that's
gonna fill in the next piece.
So one S, two, two, s, two.
Now with this case, we have to continue
reading across the page, right?
Even though there's all this
stuff in the middle, we read
all the way across the boron.
So boron to neon.
This is your two P level, right?
So it's still a second line,
but it is now a P shape.
So with this, it's gonna be two P
six, because there's a total of six
columns that we're reading, right?
The boron was one, carbon was
two nitrogen, three oxygen,
four fluorine, five neon is six.
Now for the next one, we then come down to
our next line, which is sodium, magnesium,
which is three S one, three s two, and
then we'll go do aluminum and silicon.
So what that will be is three S two.
Followed by three P two.
Now when it comes to this, what we now
have to do is our Noble Gas abbreviation.
But before we do that, let's,
let me show you a trick to make
sure you ended in the right spot.
So if you remember before I
showed you that there was 14
electrons, well, there is a way
for you to double check your work.
So if you add up all of the, the
exponents here, the sub, the superscripts,
So we have 2, 2, 6, 2 and two.
So add those together.
Two plus two is four.
Four plus six is 10, six or 10 plus
two is 12 and, and 12 plus two is 14.
So if you add up all these numbers
together, this makes a total of
14 electrons, which allows you
to be able to see that we have
that complete number of them.
It's a, it's a check.
You want to check yourself.
Um, now what else is there?
Same thing as before, we're gonna look for
the noble gas that's above silicon here.
If you look over, well, what's above it?
Well, we can see neon is
right above it, right here.
So neon is your, your choice of gas.
Um, so we will write
that in is neon right?
And what that is gonna be representing
here is all of the, uh, All the individual
guesses that are up on the second level.
So I wrote this like this on purpose,
so that way you can see like, okay, all
these ones are neon's electrons, right?
If you were to figure out the
configuration for it, one SS two
two s, two two P six, that is
neon, that has its 10 electrons.
So now all we have to do is write
three s two three P six, and
that would be your configuration.
Let's do the D orbital example.
Okay.
With the D orbital example,
this one is a longer problem.
Same with the F orbital one.
So with the d orbital, what we're gonna
be looking for is vanadium in this case.
So with the V, so we can see
vanadium is right over here.
So this one has a number of 23 above it.
So it has 23 electrons.
So when you go through this, double
check your math to make sure you're
getting there the same as last time.
We start from the top and we're going
to be reading from, from left to
right as we're going through these.
Now the thing with the D orbital, there
is a different trick when it comes to the
N number or the total number of columns.
So if you kind of remember
that picture from before.
So let's, uh, go back to that
real quick over to this picture.
One thing that I forgot to mention before
is that the D level and the F levels,
quantum numbers are different than before.
Now the quantum number was
referring to the columns.
So s is normal, p is normal.
So they're just your normal N numbers.
With d, what we actually do is we do
N minus one for those levels, and then
with F we do N minus two for our levels.
Let's go back to our example to
show how that's gonna be used.
So like I was mentioning, we're
gonna be reading this like a book.
So what we will do is we will
start from top to bottom.
We'll start with the one s two
area, so we will do that first.
So hydrogen helium.
Then we'll go down to lithium beryllium.
So one s, two Ss two, we'll
go from boron to neon.
Then we'll go to the next row, which
is three S two, then three P six.
Now when we get to the fourth level,
which is right here, so uh, potassium
and calcium, that's gonna be four s two.
Now, like I mentioned, D is N minus one.
So what we are going to
do is we have 1, 2, 3.
This is not gonna be four D, but it's
going to be three D three, and that is
your electron configuration for vanadium.
Now we can double check ourselves.
We can add up all these individual
values, and we should get 23.
So if we do two plus two, that is four.
Four plus six is 10.
10 plus two is 12.
12 plus six is 18.
18 plus two is 20.
20 plus three is 23, right?
We have our math.
So how can we try to sum up all
these individual values as a
Noble Gas configuration, being
that we have everything right?
Remember all these top numbers here, these
are all gonna be our, um, our noble gas.
And what we're gonna do is find
the noble gas that is one above it.
And we can see that we
have argon right here.
So argon is our noble gas, and
then we carry down everything else.
Now, the cool thing about this is it
helps show, helps it make it a lot easier.
It's easier to write, it's
quicker, but it all depends on
your homework and your exams.
Exactly.
What are you being asked?
If it's says complete
or full configuration?
Write the full one out.
If it's noble, guess save yourself the
time and the energy and the anxiety.
Let's do an F orbital example.
Okay.
With an F orbital example,
this is a tougher problem.
Exactly.
What do we have to do
while going through this?
We have to find Neodinium nd
so let's try to find it now.
The F orbitals are always down here
at the bottom of the periodic table,
so it's like this extra little piece.
Now, one thing, depending on which
version of the periodic table you have,
whether it's the new one or the old one,
uh, you might have counted here earlier.
It wasn't exactly 14 columns
on mine, there's 15 for mine.
Every one of 'em is different.
Check yours to see which one you have.
Now the reason is, is these two
elements, they actually are right here.
Um, and usually you'll always have
a, a piece that tells you like, Hey,
this is where you start counting
them, uh, which is right in here.
Which is where those f
orbitals are gonna start.
So Nd is right at this spot.
Um, so let's go through the example so I
can show you how to, how to go about it.
Um, and what we're gonna do is we're
gonna read our periodic table like normal
and we'll get down to the six level.
So right here, 1, 2,
3, 4, 5, and then six.
And then I'll show you how
to do the f orbital example.
So with this, we kind of
just show it like normal.
So we start off from the top,
right, it would be one Ss two,
then it would go down to two.
Then it's 5, 4, 5.
So let, let me write down all those
individual numbers so that way
it'll help you see them on here.
So this is gonna be uh, one
s, 1s, 2s, and so forth.
So let me fill all these in so that
way you can have them for yourself.
So we can see how this is going to
be changing and you can really see
how all those individual levels are
different, um, especially when it
comes to S P D and then f as well.
So that way we have all
those individual levels.
Okay, so let's fill in our numbers.
'cause pretty much we have
complete orbits from here on out.
So we are gonna do five.
Five Ss is next, and then
we will fill in the rest.
So let, let's fast forward
till I get that little bit.
Okay.
Now we are at six S two, so six Ss two.
What we can see here is now
we all of a sudden have the
lanthanides, which is our F block.
So our goal is to get to year.
So what this will be is
we'll have our six s two.
And then it's N minus two, so it's
gonna be four F, and then being
that it goes to the third spot.
So keep in mind that these belong here.
These are the D group
on my periodic table.
So we start at um, cerium,
and then we go 1, 2, 3.
So this is gonna be 4f^3 for our example.
The intervals are really freaking
hard when you have to do them.
Hopefully you don't have to do many.
Usually it's a homework example.
Very rarely do you see them on exams.
So Noble Gas Configuration,
how do we go about it?
Well, same as before we
end around the P group.
So all of these are going to be,
uh, we're gonna style all these
to be red so we can show all those
that these are gonna be red here.
And we have these ones as red too.
And then also this one, I've missed one.
Okay, so all of those are
gonna be your, your gas.
So where do we go from this one?
Xenon is the gas of choice 'cause
it's right above Neodinium and it's
gonna be six s two four F three.
So that's how to go through all
of these individual examples.
So whether it's an f orbital,
s orbital p orbital, d orbital.
Hopefully this video helped you be
able to see electronic configuration.
Remember, it's an organization tool.
It's an exact same
pattern every single time.
Um, I hope that this helped, and
if this method didn't try looking
up the diagonal method on YouTube.
There's a lot of really good resources
out there for that method as well.
I will have future videos in the future.
I might have one eventually later
in this semester or future semesters
on the diagonal method as well.
I hope to see you all
later and this has been Dr.
Dan, and please hit that
like and subscribe button
to help support the channel.
It's been growing a lot, and I hope
to see you back for future videos.
All right, I'll see you all later now.
Bye now.